"Iron-Deficiency Anemia: The Best Treatment
and Are Vegetarians at Higher Risk?"
Based on a study
of nearly half a million people
followed for eight years,
higher consumption
of unprocessed red meat
and processed meat was
associated with higher risks
of the #1 killer
of men and women,
heart disease,
as well as pneumonia,
diverticular disease—
outpouchings of the colon wall—
colon polyps, and diabetes.
Higher poultry intake was
associated with higher risks
of gastroesophageal
reflux disease—
acid reflux, gastritis,
and duodenitis,
which is inflammation of the
stomach lining and intestines,
as well as diverticular disease
of the colon,
gallbladder disease,
and diabetes.
And all these
were after taking into account
a vast array of other factors,
including age, sex, class,
education, employment,
smoking, exercise,
even dietary factors,
like total fruit
and vegetable intake,
and how much fiber they may be
getting from whole grains,
for instance, to help account
for dietary quality.
So, the higher rates of disease
really did seem to be linked
to the amount of meat
they were eating
instead of other factors.
The researchers
even adjusted for BMI,
meaning it wasn't just
because those eating meat
tend to be heavier.
The bottom line is that
higher consumption of meat,
including chicken,
is associated
with higher risks
of several
common disease conditions,
but higher meat consumption
was significantly associated
with a lower risk
of one condition,
iron deficiency anemia.
In a previous video,
I talked about how vegetarians
might be right in
the ferritin sweet spot,
with iron stores low enough
to help prevent iron
toxicity-related diseases
like diabetes and cancer,
but high enough to avoid
iron deficiency anemia.
So, they appear to have
the best of both worlds.
Low iron stores
to keep free radicals down
but not enough to result
in higher rates of anemia.
At least,
that's what we used to think
until this study
of British vegetarians
was published.
Based on the anemia rates
of hundreds of thousands
of regular red meat eaters,
those eating red meat
only a few times a week,
or the thousands of people
who stuck to poultry, to fish,
were vegetarian
versus hundreds of vegans.
Among white men,
only the fish eaters
appeared to have significantly
higher rates of anemia.
Among premenopausal women,
the infrequent red meat eaters
had higher rates
than the regular
red meat eaters,
and those who skipped
red meat altogether
had higher rates
except the vegans.
About 9% of regular meat-eating
menstruating women had anemia,
compared to 10% of those who
ate red meat less frequently,
compared to about 13% of those
who didn't eat red meat at all,
but only 8% of vegans
were anemic.
And postmenopausal women
showed the same trend,
about 3% higher anemia rates
in those who skipped red meat.
British Indian participants
had higher anemia rates
across the board,
with significantly higher rates
in vegetarian men
and older women,
though not necessarily
among reproductive age women,
but the rates were
extremely high regardless.
The prevalence among
American women is more like 9%.
Iron deficiency anemia
can have serious consequences,
like this young vegan woman
who temporarily lost
part of her vision
due to a severe case of it.
She started out with low iron
stores from her diet,
then experienced menorrhagia,
meaning excessively
heavy menstrual bleeding,
which is in fact
the most common cause
of iron deficiency anemia,
regardless of diet,
heavy menstrual bleeding.
There's lots of hormonal and
nonhormonal medical treatments
to treat the cause of anemia
by lightening menstrual flow,
but in terms
of treating anemia,
oral iron supplements
are considered
the first line treatment,
though in serious cases
rapid repletion
of blood levels
using IV iron can be used.
Intravenous iron
may also be used
in the setting
of inflammatory bowel disease,
since oral iron can be toxic
to the lining of the intestines,
potentially worsening
the disease process.
However, iron supplements
may result
in adverse gastrointestinal
effects in everybody,
such as abdominal pain,
constipation, or nausea.
Nearly 75% of patients
taking iron supplements
experience side effects
which ultimately result
in one in four
ceasing treatment,
predominantly due
to gastrointestinal problems.
Even if you don't
experience symptoms,
iron supplements
may exacerbate inflammation
or hurt your microbiome,
reducing the abundance
of beneficial microbes,
while increasing the abundance
of deleterious ones.
And, of course, iron supplements
are a short-term strategy,
while dietary interventions
can be considered
a more long-term strategy.
And indeed,
you can successfully treat
iron-deficiency anemia
with diet alone,
usually by increasing
consumption of iron-rich foods
like iron-fortified grains,
along with vitamin C-rich foods
or beverages
that help
with iron absorption.
The healthiest iron sources
are legumes
(beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils),
whole grains,
dark green leafy vegetables,
certain fruits,
like dried apricots,
and nuts and seeds.
Although non-iron
dietary factors,
such as not drinking tea
with meals
or adding vitamin C-rich foods,
don't have as much effect
on iron absorption
as we used to think,
it can't hurt
to drink tea separately,
and include
vitamin C-rich foods,
such as citrus,
tropical fruits,
bell peppers,
or broccoli with your meals.
If you do need
iron supplements,
the optimal dosing may be
60 to 120 mg of ferrous iron—
so, like ferrous sulfate,
or ferrous gluconate,
ferrous lactate,
ferrous fumarate,
or ferrous succinate—
though ferrous bisglycinate
may have at least twice
the bioavailability.
So, you can take half the dose
and thereby suffer
fewer side effects,
given with vitamin C
on alternate days.
So, every other day
rather than taken every day.
Oral iron should generally
be taken on an empty stomach,
at least an hour before meals.
Now, if taking it
on an empty stomach
causes pain and nausea,
you can take it with meals
which may reduce side effects
but may also reduce absorption.
Similarly, taking vitamin C
with the iron
increases its absorption,
but at the same time,
increases incidence
of gastrointestinal side effects
so, only do it
if you can tolerate it.